In these clips, we're going to talk about the proper way to remove and replace your vehicle's thermostat.
In this clip, we're going to talk about removing the serpentine belt and the serpentine belt tensioner in order to gain access to our vehicle's thermostat.
This yellow component right here is my thermostat housing.
It's got a small portion of pipe on it as you can see and goes down to the actual housing here.
It has three bolts that hold it down.
And unfortunately enough, Ford decided to bury one of them behind my serpentine belt tensioner.
On your particular vehicle, you may not necessarily have to remove a serpentine belt tensioner.
However, you may have to remove, say an alternator or an A/C compressor, what I'm going to do is go over with you the general removal procedures for a couple of these devices.
In order to remove the serpentine belt, what you have to do is relax the tensioner.
In order to remove the serpentine belt, what we have to do is release this spring-loaded tension that's applied by the tensioner.
The tensioner is spring-loaded in a clockwise direction.
As you can see, I have my double wrench here and you can see as I work it and let it go, the belt gets tighter and looser.
So, what I'm going to do is take and put enough tension on it so I can slip the belt off of my alternator and let it relax back down.
Once I have this guy out of the way, I can take and remove my belt.
Now, if my belt-not completely off of the engine but out of the way enough that I can get at the tensioner's mounting bolts.
There's one here and there's one here on the bottom.
I got my half-inch drive crafts and ratchet with my 17mm 12-point socket.
We'll take and slip it on the mounting bolt there and give it a pop to break it loose.
You're going to go ahead and repeat the same procedure for the other mounting bolts if there are any present.